<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Central Intelligence Bulletin Daily Brief
				</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Central Intelligence Agency</publisher>
				<date when="1958-08-06">6 August 1958</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Transcribed from the scanned document</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<graphic url="https://www.cia.gov/readingroom/docs/CENTRAL%20INTELLIGENCE%20BULL%5B15777404%5D.pdf"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text>
		<front xml:lang="en">
			<div type="section" xml:id="i">
				<head rend="caps">The Communist Bloc</head>
				<p n="1">Latest <persName>Khrushchev</persName>'s latest communications reflect <placeName>Moscow</placeName>'s desire for a forum to denounce Western policies in <placeName>Middle East</placeName> before sense of crisis fades; no indication that Khrushchev plans to attend UN session.
				</p>
				<p n="2"><persName>Chinese</persName> Communists further increase jet fighter strength in <placeName>Taiwan Strait</placeName> area.
				</p>
				<p n="3"><placeName>USSR</placeName> has resumes arms shipments to <placeName>Syria</placeName>.
					<milestone unit="redaction" n="1"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" xml:id="ii">
				<head rend="caps">Asia-Africa</head>
				<p n="4"><placeName>Jordan</placeName> - <persName><roleName>King</roleName> Husayn</persName> orders more army units into <placeName>Amman</placeName> to prop up security.
				</p>
				<p n="5"><persName>Algerian</persName> rebels planning attack on <persName>Europeans</persName> on or about <date when="1958-08-20">20 August</date>.
				</p>
				<p n="6"><placeName>Pakistan</placeName> - <persName><roleName>President</roleName> Mirza</persName> and former <persName><roleName>Prime Minister</roleName> Suhrawardy</persName> have hammered out a political truce.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" xml:id="iii">
				<head rend="cap">The West</head>
				<p n="7"><persName>British</persName> officials fear effect on their forces in <placeName>Jordan</placeName> if <persName>US</persName> troops withdraw from <placeName>Lebanon</placeName>.
				</p>
				<p n="8">Plotting continues in <placeName>Paraguay</placeName>; <persName><roleName>President</roleName> Stroessner</persName> has ordered arrests, and he retains loyalty of the military.
				</p>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body xml:lang="en">
			<div type="section" xml:id="I">
				<pb n="i"/>
				<head rend="caps">The Communist Bloc</head>
				<p><hi rend="italic">Latest <persName>Khrushchev</persName> letters</hi>: Having failed to force the <plaecName>United States</plaecName> and <placeName>Britain</placeName> to accept <placeName>Soviet</placeName> terms for five-power summit talks, <persName>Khrushchev</persName> now hopes to use a special session of the <orgName>UN General Assembly</orgName> to denounce <persName>American</persName> and <persName>British</persName> actions in the <placeName>Middle East</placeName> before events bring about a further easing in the crisis atmosphere which <placeName>Moscow</placeName> seeks to maintain. <persName>Khrushchev</persName> apparently had hoped to use a five-power heads-of-government meeting to gain Western recognition of the <placeName>USSR</placeName>'s claim to a major voice in the <placeName>Middle Eastern</placeName> affairs; this effort appears to have been temporarily suspended. His letters contain no indication that he plans to appear before the General Assembly to present the <placeName>USSR</placeName>'s case personally. <milestone unit="redaction" n="1"/> (Page 1) <pb n="ii"/>
				</p>
				<p><hi rend="italic">Communist <placeName>China</placeName> - <placeName>Taiwan</placeName></hi>: Twenty-nine <persName>Chinese</persName> Communist jet fighters were photographed on 4 August on <placeName>Lungchi airfield</placeName>, about 30 miles inland from <placeName>Amoy</placeName>, according to the <orgName>Chinese Nationalist Air Force</orgName>. This move places Communist fighters directly opposite <placeName>Taiwan</placeName> and in the immediate vicinity of the major Nationalist-held offshore islands for the first time. <milestone unit="redaction" n="2"/> On <date when="1958-07-27">27</date> and <date when="1958-07-29">29 July</date>, at least 36 MIG's moved into <placeName>Swatow</placeName>, another of the Chinese Comuunist coastal airfields opposite <placeName>Taiwan</placeName>. <milestone unit="redaction" n="3"/>
				</p>
				<p>The build-up in the Communist air defense posture is probably designed to gain control of the air in <placeName>Fukien Province</placeName> and over the offshore islands as well. In addition, the Communists have improved their capability to interdict support for the Nationalist-held offshore islands. The greatest danger at the moment is that the Nationalists may react vigorously to any further Communist air moves, particularly into the coastal airfields in <placeName>Fukien Province</placeName>. However, <persName>Chiang Kai-shek</persName> told the <persName><roleName>US ambassadar</roleName></persName> in <placeName>Taipei</placeName> he would honor his commitments to consult with US authorities before ordering any attacks on the mainland. He requested additional military equipment and a US "show of force." <milestone unit="redaction" n="4"/> (page 4) (Map)
				</p>
				<p><hi rend="italic"><placeName>USSR</placeName> - <placeName>UAR</placeName></hi>: Soviet arms including 25 tanks--possibly T-54's--are again being shipped to <placeName>Syria</placeName>. Three shiploads of military equpment were delivered to <placeName>Latakia</placeName> in <date notAfter="1958-07-31" notBefore="1958-07-01">July</date>, the first such shipments since last May. Another vessel was unloading arms as of <date when="1958-08-02">2 August</date> and a fifth is en route to the port. <milestone unit="redaction" n="5"/> (Page 6)
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" xml:id="II">
				<head rend="cap">Asia-Africa</head>
				<p><hi rend="italic">Jordan</hi>: The position of King Husayn's government continues to deteriorate. Should the present pro-Western government fall, action by Israel and the UAR to secure portions of Joranian territory seems almost inevitable. The King has brought more army units into the capital to prop up local security. <milestone unit="redaction" n="6"/> (Page 7) <pb n="iii"/>
				</p>
				<p><hi rend="italic">Algeria</hi>: The Algerian rebels are reported to be planning an attack on the European population on or about 20 August. <milestone unit="redaction" n="7"/> (Page 9)
				</p>
				<p><hi rend="italic">Pakistan</hi>: Intensive political maneuvering apparently has culminated in an agreement between President Mirza and his chief rival, former Prime Minister Suhrawardy. This should improve political stability and make it more likely that the national elections actually will be held as expected in February. The present government of Prime Minister Noon is to continue until elections. Suhrawardy would then become prime minister and support Mirza's re-election. <milestone unit="redaction" n="8"/> (Page 10)
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" xml:id="III">
				<head rend="cap">The West</head>
				<p><hi rend="italic">Britain - Jordan</hi>: British officials show increasing anxiety over the position of British troops in Jordan, and hope that the US will continue to retain forces in Lebanon, or else send some to Jordan. Establishment of a regular supply route through Aqaba lessens the impact of Israel's banning of overflights. <milestone unit="redaction" n="9"/> (Page 11)
				</p>
				<p><hi rend="italic">Paraguay</hi>: The government claims it has evidence of several subversive plots, including an attempt on the life of President Stroessner. The President has ordered many arrests; and the military, which seems loyal to the regime, can probably assure the inauguration of the dictator for a second term on 15 August. <milestone unit="redaction" n="10"/> (Page 12)
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" xml:id="IV">
				<pb n="4"/>
				<head><hi rend="italic">Taiwan Strait Situation</hi></head>
				<p>On 4 August, at least 29 Chinese Communist jet fighters were sighted on Lungchi Airfield, about 30 miles from the coast in the Amoy area.
				<!-- More texts here. -->
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
